<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Analysis on Matthew J. Sigal</title>
    <link>http://www.matthewsigal.com/categories/data-analysis.html</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Analysis on Matthew J. Sigal</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Matthew J. Sigal</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://www.matthewsigal.com/categories/data-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Continuous Interactions in Multiple Regression</title>
      <link>http://www.matthewsigal.com/post/continuous-interactions-in-multiple-regression.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.matthewsigal.com/post/continuous-interactions-in-multiple-regression.html</guid>
      <description>After some brief conversations during consulting about how to construct interaction terms for multiple regression (and why centering variables beforehand is important), I put together a short demonstration of R’s default behaviour when using the built-in convenience functions (specifically *, but also applies to formulas that use ^).
The vignette is posted here: http://rpubs.com/mattsigal/reg_interactions
The short-version: *, when used with summary() does not center the variables, and so models will have issues with VIF.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Grammar of (Interactive) Graphics</title>
      <link>http://www.matthewsigal.com/post/the-grammar-of-interactive-graphics.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.matthewsigal.com/post/the-grammar-of-interactive-graphics.html</guid>
      <description>I gave a presentation today (October 21st, 2013) on the “Grammar of (Interactive) Graphics”. The overarching ideas behind the talk were to discuss Leland Wilkinson’s Grammar of Graphics, its implementation in the R package ggplot2, to introduce some fundamental characteristics of interactive graphics and their present implementations (via R and some JavaScript libraries), and discuss how interactive graphics can be understood within the Grammar of Graphics theory. The presentation concluded with a discussion of one of Hadley Wickham’s latest R packages, ggvis, which refines the previous packages grammar to include some of these goals.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>